Robert Dennis Reid
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Robert Dennis Reid papers
1961-1977
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Reid, Robert Dennis
0.2 linear feet
This small collection of papers of African-American artist and educator Robert Dennis Reid consists primarily of correspondence (75 items), and scattered exhibition catalogs and announcements, clippings, and photographs and slides of Reid's artwork. There is also one photograph of Reid. Within the correspondence are six letters from Romare Bearden.
Provenance
Robert Dennis Reid donated his papers to the Archives of American Art on November 4, 1974.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
African-American painter and fine arts professor Robert Dennis Reid was born in Atlanta, Georgia in 1924. He studied at Clark College in Atlanta from 1941-1943 and continued his art education at the Art Institute of Chicago. Later, Reid studied at the Parsons New School of Design in New York City.
Throughout his career, Reid exhibitied at Grand Central Art Gallery in New York City, the UCLA Gallery, and the Whitney Museum of American Art. In addition, the 1st World Festival of Negro Artists in Dakar, Senegal (1965) featured Reid's work. Reid held positions as a professor of painting and drawing at the Summit Art Center in New Jersey and the Rhode Island School of Design. He also exhibited with the U.S. State Department in the "Arts in the American Embassies" program. To supplement his income, Reid worked for the United States Post Office in the evenings. Robert Dennis Reid died in 2002.
Scope and Content Note
This small collection of papers of African-American painter and fine arts professor Robert Dennis Reid consists of a resume, 75 letters to and from Reid, scattered exhibition catalogs and announcements, clippings, and photographs and slides of Reid's artwork. There is also one photograph of Reid. Within the correspondence are six letters from Romare Bearden, as well as correspondence with Grand Central Modern Gallery, Grand Central Galleries, University of Notre Dame Art Gallery, Fairweather Hardin Gallery (Chicago), Rose Fried Gallery, Galerie Darthea Speyer (Paris), Benson Gallery, ADI Gallery, Inc. (San Francisco, Calif.), and the Young Gallery (Calif.).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 4 series:
Series 1: Biographical Information, circa 1960s (Box 1; 1 item)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1; 75 items)
Series 3: Printed Material, circa 1961-1975 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 4: Photographs and Slides, 1964-1977 (Box 1; 2 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Art teachers -- New York (State)-- New York; Art galleries, Commercial; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs
Names:
ADI Gallery; Bearden, Romare, 1911-1988; Galerie Darthea Speyer (Paris, France); Fairweather Hardin Gallery; Grand Central Art Galleries; Grand Central Moderns (Gallery); Rose Fried Gallery (New York, N.Y.); University of Notre Dame Art Gallery
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, circa 1960s, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 item)
  This series consists of one resume of Robert Dennis Reid.
  - Resume, circa 1960s (Box 1 (pam), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, circa 1960s-1970s, Series 2:; (Box 1; 75 items)
  Found here is correspondence to and from Robert Dennis Reid, including six letters from Romare Bearden and correspondence with Grand Central Modern Gallery, Grand Central Galleries, University of Notre Dame Art Gallery, Fairweather Hardin Gallery (Chicago), Rose Fried Gallery, Galerie Darthea Speyer (Paris), Benson Gallery, ADI Gallery, Inc. (San Francisco, Calif.), and the Young Gallery (Calif.)
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically with undated materials at the end.
  - Correspondence, circa 1965-1976 (Box 1 (pam), Folder 2)
- Printed Material, circa 1961-1975, Series 3:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  This series contains exhibtion announcements, catalogs, press releases and newspaper clippings concerning Robert Dennis Reid's shows and activities as an artist.
  - Clippings, 1968-1975, circa 1960s (Box 1 (pam), Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 11961-1975, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1 (pam), Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Press Releases, 1964, 1971, 1974 (Box 1 (pam), Folder 5)
- Photographs and Slides, 1964-1977, Series 4:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  This series consists of one photograph of Robert Dennis Reid as well as slides and photographs of his works of art.
  - Robert Dennis Reid, 1973 (Box 1 (pam), Folder 6)
  - Works of Art, 1964, 1968-1970, 1973, 1977 (Box 1 (pam), Folder 7)